Guide to the Tri-State Commission and WMATA records, 1937-1988 MS2402
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Tri-State Commission and Washington Metropolitan Transportation Authority (METRO) records
1937-1988
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Alper, Jerome M.
MS2402
5.5 Linear Feet 12 document boxes
The material in this collection relate to the Tri-State Commission and Metro. The donor, Jerome M. Alper was a lawyer who helped draft the interstate compact that created the regional rapid rail system.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in original order received by the donor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jerome Alper.
Scope and Contents
The material in this collection include correspondence, reports, memorandum, and photographs. These materials relate to the Tri-State Commission and Metro.
Biographical / Historical
Jerome M. Alper (b. August 1914 d. November 3, 2020) was a lawyer who helped draft the interstate compact that created the regional rapid rail system. Mr. Alper was born in Brooklyn, N.Y. He was a graduate of what is now the University of Tennessee at Chattanooga and the University of Chicago's law school. He served in the Navy in the Pacific during World War II. He began his career at the Securities and Exchange Commission after the war and was later in private practice. His clients included the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, where he was special counsel. Alper. wrote the book History of the Negotiations of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority.
Related Materials
From MS2214 Jerome Alper interview part 1
From MS2214 Jerome Alper interview part 2
Transportation -- Washington Metropolitan Area; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Alper, Jerome M.
- Tri-State - Consent Legislation correspondence, 1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Tri-State - Consent Legislation House Hearings, 1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation (JMA) House Debate, undated; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation Legislation, 1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation Memoranda, 1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation Press Releases, 1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation Supporting Material, undated; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation Testimony - House Hearings, 1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation Work Papers, 1937-1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Tri-State Commission - NVTD Current, 1964-1965; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (Agenda of Meetings) and notice to members of Commission, 1962-1966; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Tri-State Commission Transportation Planning Board [1/2], 1965; MS2402 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Tri-State Commission Transportation Planning Board [2/2], 1965 April; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Tri-State - Washington Suburban Transit District - Work Papers, 1965; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- NCTA Transportation Plan [1/2], 1963-1965; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- NCTA Transportation Plan [2/2], 1962-1965; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Tri-State Commission (Comments on NCTA 1964-1965 Proposals), 1960-1965; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Tri-State comments on NCTA 1963 Proposals (S. 1647, H.R. 6633 and 7249 and H.R. 8929), 1963-1966; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Northern Virginia Transp. District (correspondence), 1963-1968; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- NVTC - Virginia Metropolitan Areas Transportation Study Commission, 1968; MS2402 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- WMATA legislation [Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority], 1964; MS2402 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Legislation and reports NCTA 1960 and Joint Commission Washington Metro Area Problems, 1959-1960; MS2402 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Joint Committee on Washington Metropolitan Area Problems, 1958; MS2402 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Tri-State Commission - labor, 1963-1964; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Tri-State Commission - management companies, 1961-1965; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Tri-State Commission -physical facilities committee, 1966; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Tri-State Proprietary Compact (plan of financing), 1963-1964; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Tri-State Commission - press releases, 1965; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Tri-State Commission - proprietary Compact (federal negotiator), 1963; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Tri-State Commission - proprietary compact (legal), 1964; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Tri-State Commission (proprietary comm.), 1962-1963; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Tri-State Commission transportation planning board correspondence, 1965; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Tri-State Commission Virginia transportation district (law), 1964-1965; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Tri-State Commission Virginia transportation district (work papers), 1963-1964; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Tri-State Commission Virginia action on compact, 1966; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation cooperative arrangements between NCTA and Authority, 1966-1967; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Tri-State Consent Legislation law, 1966; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Tri-State joint steering committee, 1964-1965; MS2402 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Tri-State liaison finance committee, 1966; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Tri-State Proprietary Compact 1965 NCTA legislation, 1965-1967; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Tri-State - Washington Suburban Transit District - law (commission), 1965-1968; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Joint Transportation Commission meeting, 1964 May 22; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Comments by joint transportation commission on the report of the NCTA, undated; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- National Capital Transportation Act of 1960, 1959-1960; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- NCTA annual reports [Tri-State], 1966; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- National Capital Transportation Authority Compact [staff draft], undated; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Metropolitan Area Transit study (data submitted by Public Service Commission Maryland [Capital Transit Co.], 1955; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- NCTC Highways [1/2], 1958-1960; MS2402 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- NCTC Highways [2/2], 1958-1960; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Organization and procedure manuals, 1969-1975; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Regulation Compact background, 1953-1954; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Transit statements, testimony, compact, 1964, undated; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Commission executive of compact, 1955-1959; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- WMATA compact negotiations memos, undated; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Financing plan [WMATA], 1966; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- WMATA National Capital Transportation Authority, 1964; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- WMATA organization, undated; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Joint Transportation Commission / Tri-State Commission papers, 1964; MS2402 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Tri-State Commission budget during negotiations [1/2], 1964-1966; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Tri-State Commission budget during negotiations [2/2], 1962; MS2402 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Tri-State budget for Authority (JMA), 1966-1967; MS2402 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (minutes) [1/3], 1961-1964; MS2402 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (minutes) [2/3], 1962 March - July; MS2402 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (minutes) [3/3], 1962 March - August; MS2402 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (newspaper clippings), 1966; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (work papers), 1964; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Tri-State Commission - Proprietary Compact (work papers), 1963-1964; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Tri-State Commission - source materials, 1959-1960; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Transit Compact (metropolitan area, Washington, D.C.) legal-law, 1958; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- [Joint Transition Comission - Alper financials], 1964-1966; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Tansit - Federal Corporation - NCPC (comments and legislation), 1959; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Transit - Federal Corporation (N.C.P.C.), 1959-1960; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Transit - Federal Corporation and Proprietary Compact, 1959-1960; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Key Questions on Urban Transporation by Paul H. Gerhardt and John H. Nixon, 1962 September 10; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Washington Gas Light Company Charter, 1848; 1953; MS2402 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Work papers [Transporation], 1958, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority Compact, 1964 September 1; MS2402 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- WMATA report basic info [1/3], 1965-1966; MS2402 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- WMATA report basic info [2/3], 1965-1966; v (Box 9, Folder 4)
- WMATA report basic info [3/3], 1965-1966; MS2402 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Resident Engineer Diary Job No. 1A0171 book 1 of 2, 1979 February 8 - 1980 October 9; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  General Note
  The engineer is R. DeSouza. He used the initials NTP which may represent a location.
- Resident Engineer Diary Job No. 1A0171 book 2 of 2, 1980 October 10 -1981 July 31; MS2402 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  The engineer is R. DeSouza. He used the initials NTP which may be a location.
- Resident Engineer Diary Job No. 1A017A, 1983 June 2 - 1984 May 9; MS2402 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Derwood Circle Extension. Two engineers: Engineer Gerald T. LeFevre from June 3, 1983 and then Craig L. Maxey January 1, 1984
- Monthly progress photos 809.2 A-17dc [Derwood Circle Extension], 1983; MS2402 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Monthly progress photos 809.2 A-17dc [Derwood Circle Extension], 1983-1984; MS2402 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Derwood Circle Extension photos, 1979-1984; MS2402 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Derwood Circle Extension schematics, 1982; MS2402 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- WMATA - Bus Trust #W 92.b, 1972; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- WMATA - Bus Trust 92.c, 1973; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- WMATA - Capital Contributions Interim Agreement, 1976; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- WMATA - Commuter Service #110, 1969-1972; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Memorandom of Understanding [WMATA] #W 89.b, 1972-1973; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Second Interim Capital Contribution Agreement [WMATA] #W96A, 1979; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Service Levels and Constraints [WMATA] #W89.c, 1973; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- WMATA - W.M.A.T.A. Compact, 1963; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- A Preliminary report on Labor Management Relations for the National Capital Transportation Agency, 1962; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Capital Transit Company [1/2], 1954; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Capital Transit Company [2/2], 1954; MS2402 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Capital Transit Company - purchase, 1960; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Statement of Jerome M. Alper in support of H.J. Res 402, 1959; MS2402 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- History of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transportation Compact by Jerome M. Alpert, 1988 April; MS2402 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- History of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transportation Compact Appendices by Jerome M. Alpert, 1988 April; MS2402 (Box 12, Folder 4)